Shalom. Today's דף כ daf kaf and we pick up at the
bottom of י"ט עמוד ב' yud tet amud bet and we are
continuing with the things that, you know, a new משנה Mishnah about
things you can, interactions with the non-Jewish pagan world. The previous משנה
Mishnah had taught about building with them, right? Building certain things which
are related to their courts or violence or not allowed, but building,
building stadia that got into a whole מושב לצים Moshav Letzim discussion,
a whole, a whole nice digression and focus there about תלמוד תורה
Talmud Torah again, as we have sort of spoken about, but emphasizing
that the real line of division for the Rabbis was not so
much pagan, you know, and עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah but it was
really about the frivolities and the seductions of the larger world contrasted
to a world of תורה ומצוות Torah u-Mitzvos particularly of תורה. Torah.
Although within the whole רבי חנינא בן תרדיון Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon
story, the idea that it's not just תורה, Torah, it's תורה ומעשים
טובים Torah u-Ma'asim Tovim was another important theme. Anyway, so we continue
with that with our משנה Mishnah and it ended by saying that
you don't build the, when you get to the niche in which
the idol is put in the bathhouse, you, you know, you don't
participate in that building. So here we get to the משנה Mishnah
and there's a fascinating question here about the first line because the
first line of the משנה Mishnah says ואין עושים תכשיטין לעבודת כוכבים,
Ve-ein osin tachshitin l'avodat kochavim,
you don't make jewelry presumably to bedeck the idol, which would sort
of seem obvious if you can't even make the niche. קטלאות ונזמים
וטבעות, Katla'ot v'nezamim v'taba'ot,
these different types of jewels, of jewelry. A קטלא katla is probably
like a necklace, a נזם nezem is probably like a nose ring,
a טבעת taba'at is a ring. רבי אליעזר אומר בשכר מותר, Rabbi
Eliezer omer besachar mutar, as long as you're being paid, it's okay.
That's a good Jewish approach: as long as you're getting paid for
it. Which is like a little bit bizarre, like why is that
מותר mutar just because you're getting paid? And like why should he
be even allowed to keep the money? I mean, this seems so
highly problematic. It gets to the issue we discussed yesterday where the
גמרא Gemara said that בדיעבד bedi'avad even if you're making the idol
you can keep the money. Like, really? Like, maybe technically, you know,
we can talk about is it תשמישי עבודה זרה tashmishei Avodah Zarah
does it get status, etc.? But like with all the types of
stuff that when we went on a holiday, the Rabbis did, you
know, when we did business on a holiday, before a holiday, on
a holiday, at the market day, we couldn't keep it. Like, this
is all very strange. And to think that anybody would allow this
under any circumstance is quite strange. So if you look at תוספות
Tosafot there's a real question whether this line exists in the משנה.
Mishnah. It doesn't exist in a lot of manuscripts in the משנה,
Mishnah, it is not in כתב יד קאופמן Ktav Yad Kaufmann which
is the most, the best manuscript of the משנה. Mishnah. I did
not check to see if it's discussed in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, that
I should have. There is nothing in the תוספתא Tosefta that parallels
it. And if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot
says,
תוספות Tosafot is, where is the
תוספות? Tosafot?
Where is the
Yeah, הגיע לכיפה, Higi'a la-kippah, that תוספות, Tosafot, it's three from the
like it's near the top of י"ט עמוד ב'. yud tet amud
bet. He says: ואיכא דגרסינן, Ve-ish d'garsinan, so that's the last line
of the previous משנה. Mishnah. ואיכא דגרסינן ואין עושים תכשיטין לעבודת כוכבים
קטלאות ונזמים וטבעות רבי אליעזר אומר מותר. Ve-ish d'garsinan: Ve-ein osin tachshitin
l'avodat kochavim, katla'ot v'nezamim v'taba'ot, Rabbi Eliezer omer mutar. אכתי דלא גרסי,
Achei d'lo garse, it makes, that doesn't seem like that's the correct
text. דלא מסתבר שיטיר שום תנא, De-lo mistavar she-yattir shum tanna, it's
always interesting, you know, some of the time תוספות Tosafot is trying
to justify the contemporary practice that seems to be in violation of
it, of the rules. Other times, when it gets too close to
real עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah like this religious sort of sensibility comes
out. How could you even think that this could be allowed? Right?
Like when he discussed רש"י Rashi and the issue about building an
altar. דלא מסתבר שיטיר שום תנא לעשות לכתחילה תכשיטי עבודה זרה.
de-lo mistavar she-yattir shum tanna la-asot l'chatchilah tachshitei Avodah
Zarah. Okay, and it doesn't make any sense to think that anybody
could allow it. Okay, and don't say that it's allowed משום איבה
mishum eivah and ואין לומר דשרי לעשות משום איבה v'ein lomar d'sharei
l'asot mishum eivah כשאר פרק ב' ליילדת עבודה זרה k'shahr perek bet
l'yalet Avodah Zarah דלא דמי דהא ודאי איכא איבה, de-lo dami, de-ha
vadai ika eivah, maybe not helping them give birth, we'll get to
that, there's definitely איבה, eivah, they'll think you're not helping us give
birth. But here, what type of an איבה eivah is it? They'll
understand that you can't make something for their עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
Okay, and then תוספות Tosafot says at the last line: ונראה שלא
היה כתוב בספר רבינו שלמה על פירושו v'nireh she-lo haya katuv b'sefer
Rabbeinu Shlomo al perusho that רש"י Rashi didn't have this line in
his משנה. Mishnah. Why? מדלא פירש מאי קטלאות. Mi-de-lo peireish mai katla'ot.
I love this. He says since there's no רש"י Rashi commentary on
the משנה, Mishnah, it proves that רש"י Rashi didn't have it. Now
maybe רש"י Rashi just didn't have anything to say on it. But
he said no, but the word קטלאות katla'ot is an unusual word.
So had רש"י Rashi had this גירסא, girsa, he would have commented
on the word קטלאות. katla'ot. That's an interesting sort of, you know,
like sort of evidence from absence. Okay, but anyway, and there's no
גמרא Gemara on it, so there's like a major issue whether this
line, of course the funny thing is like, if it didn't belong
in the משנה, Mishnah, how the heck did it get there? You
know, it's one thing to think like, oh, I don't know, like,
you know, I mean, maybe, I don't know, there was some gloss
and somebody wrote it in, like maybe trying to justify, I don't
know why Jews were doing business in this stuff, who knows? But
to have there as a debate with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying
it's allowed, so. It's really an interesting question right that there are
some that there are
some texts that have this line and some do not. Okay our
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not going to focus on it if it
did exist it belonged in the previous משנה mishna, *Mishnah* associated with
making a ניק *Nik* in the bathhouse and now we get onto
the focus of our משנה *Mishnah* which is a different focus which
connects back to the whole discussion about selling large animals and small
animals the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said that that had a lot to
do with either concerns of bestiality or about שבת *Shabbos* but you
heard sort of my theory about whether it had more to do
with the question about Jewish presence in the land of Israel that's
particularly indicated about the fact that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* speaks about
going to the
market and
buying from them the land and our animals and their slaves in
order that clearly was in order to maintain presence in the land
of Israel. So anyway with that in mind we're also going to
now get to see our point which is about the actual issue
of the land. So is the issue about not selling
the land a concern I would say that I think the simple
sense is that it's a concern of just again Jewish presence in
the land of Israel. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to make
it more of a type of a ritual issue I mean well
partly that and partly other things. We'll see and this is going
to be both today and tomorrow. First Charlie yes Charlie what'd you
find? תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says that catlote is a Latin word which
is itself unusual. Okay
Michael. So I know you addressed this but I'm just still left
with the feeling of unease about yesterday. It feels like you're sort
of being a נבל ברשות התורה *Naval Birshut HaTorah*. How come none
of that came in? Sort of the last thing about the ניק
*Nik* and about the idol. Yeah I have to look more about
the idol. Okay let's take a look continue the משנה *Mishnah*. אין
מוכרין להם במחובר לקרקע *Ein Mochrin Lahem Bimchubar LaKarka*. You cannot sell
them it almost goes without saying that you can't sell them land.
The next משנה *Mishnah* is going to talk about renting them land
but it goes without saying you don't sell them land in the
land of Israel. But you don't even sell them things attached to
land. אבל מוכר משיקצץ *Aval Mocher Misheykateitz* but you can basically sell
it once it gets cut down which is pretty obvious. רבי יהודה
אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer, מוכר להם על מנת לקצוץ *Rabbi Yehuda Omer
Mocher Lahem Al Menat Liktoz*. You can actually sell them
standing grain on the condition that it will be cut down and
we'll see the Rabbis don't like that because then while you're waiting
for to be cut down they have some claim to the land
itself for the period that that stuff is not cut down. Okay
so again that would seem to be as I said well let's
take a look at the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. מנא הני מילי *Minani
Mili* where is this from? Including a משכון *Mashkon* in other words
a קצה *K'tzeh* if I give you a משכון *Mashkon* and the
משכון *Mashkon* is you get to take my land I shouldn't be
able to do that either. That's an interesting point that could very
well be. That's a good point about borrowing money with a lien.
מנא הני מילי *Minani Mili* where is this from? אמר רב Rav
יוסף בר חנינא דאמר קרא *Amar Rav Yosef Bar Chanina De'amar Kra*
the verse says לא תחנם lo techaneim. *Lo Techonem*. לא תכרות להם
ברית ולא תחנם *Lo Tichrot Lahem Berit Velo Techonem* do not make
for them a covenant and do not לא תחנם lo techonem *Lo
Techonem* which is so how does לא תחנם *Lo Techonem* mean so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has multiple explanations of what the word לא
תחנם *Lo Techonem* means here. And one explanation is לא תתן להם
חניה בקרקע *Lo Titein Lahem Chanayah BaKarka*. Okay do not give them
some type of a dwelling in the land. Okay now the פשט
*Pshat* of the פסוקים pesukim *Psukim* anyway is talking about the seven
Canaanite nations. So the seven Canaanite nations you're supposed to wipe them
off you're not supposed to make a covenant so of course you're
not supposed to give them a dwelling in the land. The point
though here is that obviously we're not limiting ourselves to the seven
Canaanite nations. So that's what this תוספות Tosafot. *Tosfos* discusses. Like the
first part of the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* also says לא תתחתן בם
*Lo Titchaten Bam* do not intermarry with them and surprisingly there's actually
a dominant position in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is that that only
applies to the seven Canaanite
nations that actually one thing is to talk about if they convert
will marriage even be binding. So for the seven Canaanite nations even
if they convert marriage won't be binding for the other non-Jews of
course it will be. But even for the question of a prohibition
of
intermarriage it could be that this might be a big shocker but
there might be not even a biblical prohibition of intermarriage obviously like
parents of course would
sit שבעה *Shiva* would be disastrous for the continuation of the Jewish
people but in terms of like the technical prohibition. But anyway the
beginning of the verse about making a covenant and whatever
is all about the seven Canaanites. תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* assumes assuming that we're saying that this is a real
prohibition and not as an אסמכתא asmachta. *Asmachta* that the end of
the verse לא תחנם *Lo Techonem* is even more general and is
talking about all non-Jews. Now of course this is a real big
issue because as you might know right now in Israel there have
been ראשי ישיבה *Roshei Yeshiva* whatever who have written stuff about how
using this idea as a basis
for not
selling basically trying to get rid of all non-Jews from Israel and
prohibiting Jews to sell their land
to I mean it should be more prohibited to sell it to
Christians if you think it's about עבודה זרה avodah zara *Avodah Zarah*.
But if you think about לא תחנם *Lo Techonem* is just about
anybody that's not Jewish okay then it should be even to Christians
to Arabs or whatever and using this
in a political sense. Of course in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* I
mean that's an interesting question like if we try to bracket all
the politics like what would be the answer to that? Okay but
anyway. Anyway, but in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, I mean whatever there's
plenty been written on it, but I want just to appreciate, you
know, that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is framing things, you know, in
this sort of what I would say מצווה *Mitzvah* way, the same
way it did about selling animals and making it about שבת *Shabbos*,
whereas, you know, a more simple explanation is it just had to
do with a certain, you know, policy around, you know, the tentative
Jewish presence in the Land of Israel under Roman rule and trying
to ensure its continued presence and success. And therefore, okay, in that
case, you know, there were certain times when you were like a
minority and you were, you know, and you were in a weak
position, you did not want to be selling off your land, you
know, to the dominant power.
And you know, I mean think about the reverse. I don't know
if it might be uncomfortable to think about the reverse, but you
know, but think about how amongst Arabs, somebody who sells their land
to a Jew, you know, is under tremendous pressure from the Arab
community because like we're trying to retain our little grasp here, right?
So there, this type of a ruling obviously makes sense. You know,
the point is that when it gets now applied for, you know,
used in a context where Jews are, you know, completely the dominant
power. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is framing it—so it'd be one
thing if you would have said it's like a policy statement, and
the policies could change. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here, like it
did by the animals and שבת *Shabbos*, is framing these in terms
of like technical מצווה *Mitzvah* issues, not very technical, but מצווה *Mitzvah*
issues as opposed to sort of economic, socio, you know, sort of
communal policy issues. Yes. And on the subject of Christians owning land,
the Russian Orthodox Church is the largest private landowner. Oh, that's true
actually. And the whole issue because a lot of people actually only
have like land on a—based on like a 99-year lease or something
like that. Yeah, I remember hearing about that. Okay, anyway, yeah, so
in this—in the—what—this really then is a מצווה *Mitzvah* according to at
least the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is framing it and it's absolute for
all time, right? Right. So then it becomes interesting questions because, you
know,
normal non-extremist-minded people obviously understand that this cannot apply under contemporary contexts
and then the question—all right,
that's—you can go—that is—that is for beyond the scope of this שיעור
*Shiur*. Okay, so, אם כן im ken *Im Kein*, so the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* says like this: לא תתן להם חניה בקרקע *Lo Sitein
Lahem Chaniya BeKarka*. האי לא תחנם מיבעי ליה *Hai Lo Sachonem Mibayei
Lei*, דהכי קאמר רחמנא *DeHachi Ka'amar Rachamana*. One minute, says the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, but you need לא תחנם *Lo Sachonem* to tell you
something else. לא תתן להם חן chein *Lo Sitein Lahem Chein*. I
don't know if you think that פשט *Pshat*—don't give them favor, don't
be—don't show them—it doesn't mean don't show them kindness, but don't sort
of express a sense
of—I'm trying to think of the English word for this, but like
don't express a sense of how beautiful they are. You know, don't
sort of—not flatter them, but compliment them or something. The problem here
is, seems to be the problem that you don't want this to
be a sense of—well, one of two things. Either, you know, if
you're going around praising, "Oh, you know, those churches are so gorgeous"
and דא ודא *Da VeDa*. So obviously that could be something that
could, you know, sort of—again, like hold up high the attractions of
the non-Jews and the larger world and sort of pull you away
from, you know, your own commitment within your own sort of, you
know, community or your own belief about the accomplishments. If someone says
'Feh, Jewish music, feh. You know, non-Jewish music, that's brilliant or that's
gorgeous.' Okay, you know, that doesn't make you feel good about your
own, like, you know, your own traditions and your own community and
so on. And it's another reason to sort of like, you know,
pull you outside. Especially if it's about also not just about non-Jews
in general, you know, but if it's about
like—like about things specifically related to the idolatry. You know, 'Oh my
God, that temple of Zeus is gorgeous, you should see it.' You
know, then you could particularly understand it, right? Because that's like feeding
into the seduction of idolatry, and idolatry is supposed to be something
that's under the ban, you know, that sort of you're supposed to
make repugnant. And so, okay, so don't make it like beautiful, don't
articulate its beauty. The—okay, אם כן *Im Kein*—one minute—אם כן לימא קרא
im kein leima kra, *Im Kein Leima Kra* לא תחונם *Lo Sachunam*.
Now that then it gets into this funny grammar stuff which I
don't think whatever, I'm not going to do anything with. If it
only meant don't give them חן chen. *Chein*, it would have been
תחונם *Tachunam*, תחון אותם *Tachon Otam*, תתן חן chen. להם *Sitein Chein
Lahem*. מאי לא תחנם *Mai Lo Sachonem* without the ו vav *Vav*?
So שמע מינה shma mina. תרתי *Shema Mina Tarti*. It also has
the sense of חניה *Chaniya*. I don't know how that grammar means
that anyway. והאי מיבעי ליה *VeHai Mibayei Lei*, don't you also need
it דהכי קאמר רחמנא *DeHachi Ka'amar Rachamana*—this is what the Torah says—לא
תתן להם מתנת חנם matnas chinam. *Lo Sitein Lahem Matnat Chinam* from
the word of free. Don't give them a free gift. Okay, which
is also some sense of like, I don't know, are we trying
to support, you know, the non-Jews around us? Now I want to
get to that because there are statements of support, there's statements about—about
דרכי שלום darchei shalom? *Darchei Shalom*, okay, so maybe it sort of
means—so we'll talk about that in a minute. I mean this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, I have to tell you, is a very challenging גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* from our more pluralistic or even sort of tolerant types
of attitudes. Not supposed to let them in the land, you're not
supposed to compliment them, you're not supposed to give them gifts. It's
like, you know, we're not even talking about idolaters here. Okay, now
maybe you could say we are, that is one way of dealing
with this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, to say that all of these things...
תוספות Tosafot? *Tosafot* says it's not limited to the seven Canaanite nations,
but one way of trying to limit... To say it's all limited
to idolaters. Okay, so then, you know, then you'd still have to
deal with the whole Christianity issue, discuss whether Christianity is עבודה זרה,
you know, maybe we would limit the whole scope about selling, you
know, land in Israel to Hindus, you know, who's really an idolater
nowadays? That's one way to limit the scope. But it does seem
very problematic, this whole sense of not even trying to do any
positive type of expression. One minute, Charlie. So it says, אם כן
לימא קרא, so that's the verse לא תחנם. I don't know, whatever.
מאי לא תחנם שמע מינה כולהו. mai lo techaneim shma mina kulhu.
So somehow we derive all of them from them. Now, this issue
about not giving them a free gift, I love that phrase, a
free gift. Why not just say a gift, right? So it's like,
you know, what's a free gift? So anyway, so, well, maybe no
strings attached. It also means, and this is I think how תוספות
Tosafot, interprets it, that there's no larger context for the giving. Okay,
if you're giving it to them because they're a friend, if you're
giving it to them because they need צדקה tzedakah and they're poor,
whatever, that's not a free gift. A free gift is something
totally for the purpose of, I don't know, why would you give
something totally for the purpose of, you're just feeling generous and you
see the first person on the street and you want to just
show as an act of generosity. Random acts of kind generosity. So
maybe the boys, I don't know, do that to Jews, not to
non-Jews. Anyway, look at תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says,
where is it, תוספות? Tosafot
This תוספות, Tosafot אחד גר, echad ger, so just skip in the
middle. He says like this.
No, is that it?
No, רבי יהודה אומר דברים ככתבם, Rabbi Yehuda omer devarim kichsavum, that
one, רבי יהודה אומר דברים ככתבם. Rabbi Yehuda omer devarim kichsavum. So
if you look there before the word רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, he
says like this.
So he says there are various גמרות Gemaras that speak about sending
gifts to non-Jews. So he says ותרץ רבי. v'tireitz Rebbe. The line
starts with the word ותרץ רבי. v'tireitz Rebbe. It's about eight lines
from the bottom, near פרק ג Perek Gimmel in brackets. ותרץ רבי
דבתוספתא תניא גבי נבלה רבי יהודה דהכא בעובדי כוכבים המכירו מותר. v'tireitz
Rebbe d'b'Tosefta tanya gabei neveilah Rabbi Yehuda d'hacha b'ovdei kochavim hamakiro mutar.
Oh,
if you know the non-Jew, then it's allowed. מפני שהוא כמוכרו לו.
mipnei she'hu k'mochro lo. Then it's not like a gift, then it's
like a sale, meaning there's always a sense of reciprocity. You're my
friend, you did nice things to me in the past, you'll do
nice things to me in the future, right? So because in any
context where there's some sense of reciprocity, that's not a free gift.
Okay. No, no, no, this is not about land at all. This
is not about land at all. Okay.
זו כמכירו לו. zu k'makiro lo. והא דאמרינן בפרק הדר, v'ha d'amrinan
b'Perek Hadar, אמר ליה לההוא עובד כוכבים, amar lei l'hahu oved kochavim,
תא גלוסקא מיהא לא, ta gluska miha lo, even though it was
clear from context he did not recognize him, כדמשמע התם, k'demashma hisam,
שאני התם שהיה מתלווה עמו בדרך. shani hisam shehayah mislaveh imo baderech.
Yeah, he didn't recognize him before, but there they happened to be
to be going on the way together. You know, so somebody's going
on the way together with you, you know, you want to be
friendly. There's a reason that you want to cultivate a certain good
type of a relationship. Doesn't have to mean you have a long-standing
friendship. Okay, but you know, there's somebody you're walking along the way,
you want to be, you know, you don't want to be, you
know, you want to sort of cultivate some warmth there and some
connection. That's also allowed. So now, so now like what are the
cases you don't want to give a gift? Like somebody just סתם
stam is feeling I want to just throw away my money to
whoever I see. Okay. ואם תאמר למאן דאסר וכי לית ליה ההיא
דמפרנסין עניי עובדי כוכבים עם עניי ישראל מפני דרכי שלום? v'im tomar
l'man d'asar v'chi leis lei hahi d'mefarnesin aniyei ovdei kochavim im aniyei
Yisrael mipnei darchei shalom? Now if you say it's forbidden,
what about the idea of taking care of non-Jews together with Jews
because of דרכי שלום? darchei shalom ויש לומר דדרכי שלום אינו מתנת
חנם. v'yesh lomar d'darchei shalom eino matnas chinam.
No, in the context of דרכי שלום darchei shalom. it's not מתנת
חנם. matnas chinam. In the context of trying to cultivate good relations,
that's not מתנת חנם. matnas chinam. So if you know the guy,
if you happen to have some momentary connection to him, if in
general it's part of a policy of cultivating good relations, none of
that is מתנת חנם. matnas chinam. So it's pretty impossible to find
a case of מתנת חנם. matnas chinam. So anyway, I thought that
תוספות Tosafot was interesting, at least that limits the מתנת חנם. matnat
chinam. We're going to get to the חן issue in a minute.
Yes, Charlie. Yeah, Koren translates חנם chinam not as free but as
undeserved. Oh, okay. Undeserved. All right. Okay, I'm not sure I like
undeserved because like, a lesson from תוספות Tosafot here. Yeah, but no,
תוספות Tosafot isn't undeserved. And I mean I guess like if I'm
walking with this guy on the way and I'm just, or like
the case of, I don't know, דרכי שלום. darchei shalom? Is that
undeserved? Do they deserve it? Deserved I think is a higher standard
than like no purpose. You know, I'd much rather say for no
purpose. Okay. Where do you draw the line between being pleasant as
reciprocity and wanting דרכי שלום? darkhei shalom
Well,
the גמרא Gemara here is not making it about fraternizing. You're right,
it's a good point, but that's a good point. Like sometimes the
גמרא Gemara wants to cultivate good relationships, but it doesn't want it
to be so much that you start intermarrying. Right, so exactly how
to figure out that line is a hard question. But yeah, but
anyway, so it's never exactly clear. I mean what you suggest is
that the problem of the free gift is fraternizing.
I'm not sure that's it. Once you limit this so much, once
actually it's allowed with somebody that you know, those are the people
that you're more concerned about fraternizing. Yeah, so it doesn't seem to
me it's about fraternizing. It seems to... It seems to me like
an act of סתם stam largesse, please direct it to the Jewish
people. That's what I would read, not to the non-Jewish. It's not
about not trying to have a good relationship, דווקא davka that's allowed,
right? If you know them, דרכי שלום etc., try to cultivate a
positive relationship. But if it's סתם stam an act of largesse, please
don't give your ten million dollars to the, you know, to the,
to the museum of, you know, to the museum of, what do
you call it, natural history. No, give it to Jews, you know,
give it to the museum of, you know, to the Jewish history
museum. You know, the non-Jews have enough money, give your largesse to
the Jews. That's how I would read. After it's through with תוספות
Tosafot, it's limited to like an act of largesse, you know, yes.
That's not exactly the meaning of משנה, I mean מצוה. mitzva.
So if we're saying the פסוקים were talking about the שבע אומות.
shiva umos. תוספות Tosafot says no, the end of it, this part
the גמרא Gemara assumes is talking more broadly. But why? I mean,
he says by context, we understand that this type of a concern
תוספות Tosafot just says the rabbis assumed that the concerns expressed in
the word לא תחנם are types of concerns that are relevant beyond
the שבע אומות. shiva umos. Okay now, of course I don't know
why, for the בחנייה בקרקע bachanaya bekarka that's specifically about the שבע
אומות. shiva umos. Yeah, I don't know. So look, it's possible to
say that this is all דרבנן, derabbanan, that דאורייתא de-oraita it's all
שבע אומות. shiva umos. It's possible to say that even within the
context of this גמרא Gemara we're limiting ourselves to עובד עבודה זרה,
oved avodah zara, not to specifically non-Jews. Okay, that's the question about
what are the scope of this גמרא. Gemara Okay. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara. says like this. Okay, now, מתנת חינם, matnas chinam, מתנת
חינם גופא תנאי היא, matnas chinam gufa tannai hi,
this issue of מתנת חינם matnas chinam of a free gift is
itself a debate of תנאים. tannaim. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, לא תאכלו כל נבלה לגר אשר בשעריך תתננה ואכלה או
מכור לנכרי. Lo sochlu kol neveila lager asher bisharecha titnena va-achala o
machor lenochri. Do not eat any נבלה, neveila, any corpse of an
animal that was not slaughtered properly, give it to the stranger in
your, in your gate, meaning the dweller in your gate, which for
the rabbis is a גר תושב, ger toshav, not somebody who has
converted, or sell it to the non-Jew. Now that's already pretty, to
the, excuse me, to the foreigner. So now that's already indication. Give
it to the one in your gate, sell it to the foreigner.
Now the נכרי nochri here doesn't mean non-Jew, right, in the context
of the גמרא, Gemara the גר ger is the person who is
a resident alien, and the נכרי nochri is somebody who is visiting
from another country and just passing through. So you have a higher
responsibility to the person living in your land even if they're not
a citizen, they're a resident alien, than you do to a stranger.
And this anyway is the גמרא's Gemara, principle which we're going to
see, that גר ותושב והחייתו. ger v'toshav v'hachayito. It says וחי אחיך
עמך, v'chai achicha imach, your brother should live with you, and the
גמרא Gemara understands that that even includes a גר ger in the
context that's even a גר תושב. ger toshav. Apparently he has to
have some land to be living with you. Well, you could rent
him land. Okay anyway, but yes, but that's a good point, but
again that's the גמרא Gemara solves that because it's about specifically a
גר תושב ger toshav status. But I guess that's an interesting point
that you just made, that if somebody is a, the whole point
of a גר תושב ger toshav is that he has a, is
that he's living in Israel. So just, so that's a good point
that one way of dealing of counter-balancing this גמרא Gemara would be
to frame, say even if it applies in general to non-Jews, it
doesn't apply to גרי תושב. gerei toshav. And to say nowadays, you
know, non-Jews are גרי תושב. gerei toshav. Okay, that's interesting. But I,
you know, but that's like, it's harder to get someone in a
גר תושב ger toshav category than to get them out of an
עבודה זרה category. But you might be right. Like that's certainly, you
know, that is a clear exception, this is a clear status of
somebody who can live in the land is a גר תושב. ger
toshav. And a גר תושב ger toshav was defined rabbinically as one
who is מקבל על עצמו mekabel al atzmo yes, שבע מצוות. sheva
mitzvos. Anyway, yes, correct. So anyway, it says, so here it's about
giving it to the גר ger and selling it to the foreigner.
אין לי אלא נתינה לגר ומכירה לנכרי. Ein li ela netina lager
u-mechira lenochri. I only know that it's allowed to give it to
the גר, ger, to sell it to the foreigner. לגר במכירה מנין?
Lager bimchira minayin? How do I know that if I want to
I can sell to the גר? ger? You know, maybe if, if
the גר ger really needs it and he needs it to survive
I have an obligation to sustain him, but in general how do
I know that I'm allowed to sell to the גר? ger? תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, תתננה לגר אשר בשעריך תתננה או מכור. Titnena lager
asher bisharecha titnena o machor.
Like you just put the comma at a different place. Okay, you
put it, you know, תתננה או מכור Titnena o machor as opposed
to או מכור לנכרי. o machor lenochri. ולעובד כוכבים בנתינה מנין? U-le'oved
kochavim bin'tina minayin?
How do you know to the non-Jew that I can even give
it? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, תתננה ואכלה או מכור לנכרי, Titnena v'achala
o machor lenochri, give it and he will eat it or sell
it to the non-Jew, meaning bracket out the גר ger part. Right.
נמצאת אתה אומר, Nimtzet ata omer, right, אחד גר ואחד עובד כוכבים
בין בנתינה בין במכירה דברי רבי מאיר. echad ger v'echad oved kochavim
bein bin'tina bein bimchira divrei Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Meir really says that
they're both okay. So of course the question is so why did
the תורה Torah frame it this way? And the point is, okay,
you prioritize giving it to the גר, ger, but in principle both
are allowed. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר, omer, דברים ככתבם. devarim kichtavam.
No, it's only the way it's written. גר בנתינה ועובד כוכבים במכירה.
Ger bin'tina v'oved kochavim bimchira.
גר Ger has to be given and a, which again doesn't mean
like if, you know, you can, as תוספות Tosafot says what, I
can sell it to a Jew, I can't sell it to a
גר? ger? So, okay, but it means like if the גר ger
needs it to survive or something of that nature, but the real
point is עובד כוכבים במכירה. oved kochavim bimchira. You're not allowed to
give it to the non-Jew, you can only, you can only sell.
So the, what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda is the one that says you can't give it to
the non-Jew, he's the one about מתנת חינם, matnas chinam, you can
only sell it, but רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would disagree with this.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir allows a free gift to the non-Jew. So
the גמרא Gemara says now, שפיר קאמר רבי מאיר, Shapir ka'amar Rabbi
Meir, so Rabbi Meir made a good point. He read the verse,
he was able to chop up the verse in different ways. Pretty
funny why the גמרא Gemara thinks that that's the better read of
the verse, but maybe because the גמרא, Gemara I don't know, is
inclined that way. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda would say to you, רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda, would say to you, אי סלקא דעתך כדקאמר רבי
מאיר, ei salka da’atach kidka’amar Rebbe Meir, לכתוב רחמנא תתננה ואכלה. lichtov
Rachmana titnena ve’achala. If it wanted you to read it both ways,
to apply the verbs to both, it would have had a ו
vav to make it easier to connect the parts of the verse,
כדקאמר רבי מאיר ואכלה ומכור, kidka'amar Rebbe Meir ve'achala umachor, excuse me,
תתננה ואכלה ומכור, titnena ve’achala umachor,
and sell it. או למה לי? o lama li? Why does it
say או מכור? o machor? שמע מינה לדרשא כדכתיב shema mina lidrasha
kidchtiv to break up the verse, that you can only sell it,
you can only sell it to the non-Jew, you cannot give it,
so the position that you cannot give a free gift is the
position of רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda הוא דאסר. hu de'asar. So רבי
מאיר, Rebbe Meir,
now what would רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir say? I mean if רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir both are allowed, why is the verse framing it
this way? So he says לאקדומי נתינה דגר למכירה דעובדי כוכבים. leakdumi
netina deger limchira de’ovdei kochavim. It's to tell you that there's a
priority. Okay, yes of course you're allowed to do both, but yes
clearly there's a higher priority to take care of the גר ger
in your midst. Okay, and that you should prioritize, but in the
bottom equation, you're allowed to do both to either. רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda would say, כיון דגר אתה מצווה להחיותו kivan deger ata metzuveh
lehachayoto וכנעני אי אתה מצווה להחיותו, vechnani i ata metzuveh lehachayoto,
since a גר ger you're obligated to sustain him, like the verse
says like וחי אחיך עמך vechai achicha imach includes the גר, ger,
again
the גר ger here is not the convert, it is the גר
תושב ger toshav or the stranger dwelling in your midst, but you
don't have that obligation to the non-Jew. לאקדומי לא צריך קרא, leakdumi
lo tzarich kra, you didn't need the verse just to prioritize, prioritize
I would have known from the general obligation to sustain the גר,
ger, so therefore the fact that the verse separates it and separates
it with a ו is not just to tell me priority but
to tell me that I'm not allowed to give it to the
non-Jew, I'm only allowed to sell it. Again, but now we've limited
that to the sense of a free gift, you know we just
got through qualifying and saying there's a lot of circumstances under which
you can give it. I also want to draw your attention to
the fact about, you know as I've mentioned this before as we
go through this מסכת, Masechet, that the original text in this מסכת
Masechet when it talks about a non-Jew would either be גוי goy
or נכרי, nochri, but of course because of all this stuff, you
know the Christian church, whatever would, you know the apostates told the
Christian church about it and said all these bad things about non-Jews,
so we had to go through a period of self-censorship and make
everything say עובדי כוכבים, ovdei kochavim, it's not just some non-Jew, it's
talking about those, those star worshipers. Okay, but now you know it's
really bad when it doesn't say עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim but it
says כנעני. knani. And if you'll notice this entire text was talking
about עובדי כוכבים, ovdei kochavim, עובדי כוכבים, ovdei kochavim, which was one
degree of censorship. Okay, are we allowed to give it, sell it
to a non-Jew, you know or are we not allowed to sell
to a non-Jew? But when it got to the line you're not
required to sustain the life, which is like a, you know, which
means like you can be okay with the fact that somebody is
dying, it almost sounds like, it switched the text from just talking
about עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim to כנעני. knani. Okay, so you know
it's a really problematic text if it's talking about כנענים. knanim. So
like for example the גמרא Gemara. in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, for
example the question about is גזל גוי מותר? gezel goy mutar? Our
text reads גזל כנעני מותר. gezel knani mutar. So it wasn't enough
to censor it with the word אקום, Akum, we had to censor
it with the word כנעני knani because it was so offensive we
had to make it clear that it was completely talking about other
non-Jews, nobody ever, you know in the last two thousand years it
was never meant to apply, etc. Okay, even though it did, but
that's what we did. Okay. Now, the reality is though within הלכה,
Halacha, within the history of הלכה, Halacha, הלכה Halacha according to for
many, you know for פוסקים poskim that were more sort of like,
you know tolerant minded and so on, הלכה Halacha eventually caught up
to the censorship. No I'm serious, like for a while it was
a face that we presented to them even though internally we sort
of said otherwise, but eventually we, for many פוסקים, poskim, we wound
up interpreting this more for the past than for the present and
making it, you know either through saying it only applied to idolaters,
you know nowadays Christians aren't idolaters, you know whatever various ways, but
eventually, you know for some the הלכתי halachic process eventually caught up
to the, to the way we censored the texts, yes. To the
first point, Koren Sacks uncensors everything. Yeah, right. Second, so I have
a, we have always given our חמץ chametz away to non-Jews before
פסח. Pesach. According to at least רבי יהודה it seems it would
be better off to sell the חמץ. chametz. There you go. Right,
although I don't think that's a מתנת חנם. matnat chinam? Okay, well
maybe it is, I don't know, anyway it's a good question. Okay,
I mean if you have some motivation is that a מתנת חנם?
matnat chinam Anyway if you look at the תוספות, Tosafot, רבי מאיר,
Rebbe Meir, והוי צריך לאקדומי נתינה דגר למכירה
דנכרי. ve’havi tzarich leakdumi netina deger limchira denochri. The תוספות Tosafot says
ואם תאמר וכי אם יש לו לאדם חפץ למכור יתננה לגר קודם
שימכרנה לעובד כוכבים? ve’im tomar vechi im yesh lo leadam chefetz limkor
yitnena leger kodem sheyimcherena le’oved kochavim? So what you have to give
your stuff away to the, to the גר ger before you sell
it, you know, to the non-Jew? והלא אפילו ישראל אינו מצווה על
כך. vehalo afilu Yisrael eino metzuveh al kach. If you have an
object you don't have to give it to a Jew, you can
sell it to a Jew. So why here do you have to
give it to a גר ger rather than sell it to a
non-Jew? Why can't you sell it like a good business? ויש לומר
דדוקא נבלה שאינה שוה לדבר מועט לישראל, ve’yesh lomar dedavka neveila she’eina
shava ledavar muat le’Yisrael, שלא יהיו עובדי כוכבים מצויים ביניהם, shelo yehyu
ovdei kochavim metzuyim beineihem, ולגר היא שוה הרבה כשאר בשר. uleger hi
shava harbe kishar basar. So you have something that to your fellow
Jew is worth pennies, right what's a Jew going to do with
a נבלה? neveila? All right? And it's like it's not easy you
can't just go ahead and post it on eBay or go to
the market and sell it to the non-Jews because in that case
they weren't living among non-Jews. The נכרי nochri is the foreigner visiting
from a foreign land. You'd have to exert effort to sell it
to somebody living in France. Okay, but who you do have living
among you who can benefit from it is the גר. ger. So
rather than making trying to sell it for a thousand dollars, which
is its going rate in the non-Jewish market, but within here the
Jewish country it's only worth a few bucks, so rather than saying
oh I'm going to go a thousand dollars and I'll try to
ship it off to France, just give it to the גר ger
here. No you'd give a thousand dollars to the גר ger who
was living among you. I know and that's what it's telling you
you shouldn't be doing. מצוה להחיותו mitzvah l'hachayoto so maybe you can
charge him the same five dollars you would charge the Jew, you
know, so that's okay, you know, I understand but anyway but תוספות
Tosafot is just bothered like really? Like you know, you're allowed to
make a פרנסה. parnasah. So he wants to limit this idea of
this idea to prioritize, you know, to certain cases. You could also
say it's cases where the non-Jew really needs it where where the
גר ger really needs it because he's poor, he needs it to
sustain himself and then yes you do have a מצוה mitzvah to
help people, you know, and to provide them with your money to
help them. But okay. Anyway within this גמרא Gemara you have this
issue that this מתנת חנם is debated whether there's a prohibition or
whether there's a מצוה mitzvah to not do this, but then we
saw within תוספות it's read in a very narrow sense. Now we
get to the קנייה בקרקע kinyan bekarka which is the much more
political aspect we're just moving on, okay, we'll get back to that
tomorrow as well. Now we get to the other part which is
אסור דלא תחנם לא תתן להם חן. assur d'lo techonem lo titein
lahem chen.
Do not give them חן. How do they translate that in English?
Don't give them חן. Favor? Okay. Don't say favorable things about them.
Okay now is it to them or about them? Right now that's
also interesting, right? So you could understand in the simple sense you
might understand it means directly to them. Don't say to them, oh,
you're so amazing and wonderful and blah blah blah right because that
creates the sense of like I don't know looking up to them
and like you know desire to be like them and so on
so you could understand maybe if it's directly to them, but the
גמרא Gemara is now going to say that it even applies if
you're saying it about them. Okay, and then the question is about
them in general, only about their עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim like what's
the context? מסייע ליה לרב msayei lei l'Rav this supports רב Rav
דאמר רב d'amar Rav אסור לאדם שיאמר כמה נאה עבודת כוכבים זו.
assur l'adam sheyomar kama na'eh avodat kochavim zu. How beautiful is this
עבודת כוכבים. avodat kochavim. Now the this text here makes it vague
maybe you mean how beautiful is this idol. But the original text
says כמה נאה גוי זה כמה נאה גויה זו. kama na'eh goy
zeh kama na'eh goyah zu. Okay so it actually is talking about
how beautiful is this non-Jew. Oh this guy Rock Hudson he's so
handsome, you know whatever you know this whatever oh my god she's
so beautiful so so there it's not to them it's about them
and then the problem presumably is is that it is you know
what's the problem? Like we can't think that the non-Jewish world has
what to offer and has beautiful things in it? You know so
again it's hard to read this as like some biblical מצוה. mitzvah.
You could understand rabbinically that you don't want to be you know
to be having that sense of the attractions of the larger world,
right? So anyway let's see let's see what the גמרא Gemara. says.
רב Rav just said it without connecting it to the פסוק. pasuk
So רב Rav, could just be a rabbinic point. We don't want
to start going ahead and spending all of our time praising how
amazing the non-Jewish world is that'll take people out of their you
know their anchoring within the Jewish world. So when you link it
to the פסוק pasuk are we really thinking that's what the פסוק
is saying or we're making an אסמכתא. I mean same story of
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and Jesus when he says כמה נאה אכסניא
זו. kama na'eh achsanya zu. No לא היו עיניה נאות. lo hayu
eineha na'ot. I don't know anyway מיתיבי meitivei you don't have to
make every story fit with everything else. מיתיבי meitivei מעשה ברבן שמעון
גמליאל ma'aseh b'Rabban Shimon Gamliel although the גמרא Gemara here tries to
make it fit with another story. מעשה ברבן שמעון גמליאל ma'aseh b'Rabban
Shimon Gamliel שהיה
על גבי מעלה בהר הבית. shehayah al gabei ma'aleh b'Har HaBayit. He
was up there on the Temple Mount. וראה עבודת כוכבים אחת נאה.
v'ra'ah avodat kochavim achat na'ah. And he saw a beautiful non-Jewish woman.
וראה עבודת כוכבים אחת נאה v'ra'ah avodat kochavim achat na'ah right there
he was on the Temple Mount like it's you know it's almost
like that's like the world of תורה Torah that he you know
or the world of like you know God's sort of world that
should be defining him. וראה עבודת כוכבים אחת נאה v'ra'ah avodat kochavim
achat na'ah and he saw a beautiful non-Jewish woman. ביותר. b'yoter. Very
beautiful. אמר
מה רבו מעשיך ה'. amar mah rabu ma'asecha Hashem. How amazing is
what you've done God. Right why can't we appreciate the fact that
God has created a beautiful world and some of that beauty and
some of that wisdom or whatever is found amongst the non-Jews? ואף
רבי עקיבא ראה אשת טורנוסרופוס הרשע. v'af Rabbi Akiva ra'ah eshet Turnusrufus
Harasha. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva saw the wife of the evil טורנוסרופוס
Turnusrufus הרשע Harasha and she was presumably beautiful didn't say that but
presumably. רק rak he spat, ושחק v'shachak and he laughed, ובכה u'vacha
and he cried. Okay now here's the explanation. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
always does these interesting things. רק rak he spat שהיא באה מטיפה
סרוחה shehi ba'ah mitipah sruchah to remind maybe himself maybe that he
shouldn't too much I don't know lust for her or whatever or
maybe to make a statement about her that we shouldn't think that
the non-Jewish world's so beautiful in the end it all comes anything
whatever right maybe it's a general sort of like attitude anyway it
all comes from this smelly drop from semen. Okay it all came
from something it's all passing. שחק shachak he laughed דעתידה דמיגיירא d'atidah
d'migayra he could see that eventually she would convert ונסב לה v'nasiv
lah he would marry her. Of course what ever happened to his
whole beautiful love affair with רחל? Rachel? Like who is רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva married טורנוסרופוס Turnusrufus the wife of טורנוסרופוס? Turnusrufus? I understand
it's a little bizarre. Anyway so in the end haha he gets
her anyway. ובכה u'vacha דהאי שופרא בלי עפרא d'hai shufra bali afra
that this beauty will rot in the dirt. that the beauty would
be destroyed in the ground. So it's funny. On the one hand
it's nothing, it's meaningless, it's all transient, it all comes whatever. On
the other hand, it's a shame that it's all going to be
wasted eventually and it's all going to go away. I also think
it's interesting because you know whenever ר' עקיבא Rabbi Akiva laughs, there's
always this irony about his laughing, right? There around that temple הר
הבית Har HaBayit and they see the temple destroyed and he's laughing
because he says the fact that it's destroyed is really a symbol
that ultimately it's going to be rebuilt. He always sort of sees
this like ironic thing here. So here, you know also, there's like
this irony like on the one hand he's like you know he
says oh this is all meaningless and nothing and it's all the
beauty or whatever and he also sort of sees like the irony,
I guess it's a funny thing, like the fact that you can
both benefit like and enjoy the pleasures of this world while you
have it and at the same time like there's something ironic, embrace
the fact that it's all transient and it all comes from nothing
and is going to go to nothing at the same time. Okay,
but anyway, presumably he was responding to the fact that at least
the laughing was responding to the fact that he saw how beautiful
she was. So, isn't this a problem? And the גמרא Gemara in
a minute is going to get to the problem of sort of
like male lust, but right now we're not even dealing with the
lust issue. Right now we're just dealing with the fact that it
is sort of like acknowledging the beauty of the non-Jewish world. So
what's the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer? So ורב Verav and רב, Rav so
it's explaining how you know אודויי הוא דקמודה. Aduye hu dekamode. Okay,
but now so and
רב Rav would
say I guess it's ורב Verav because the problem was why רבן
שמעון גמליאל Rabban Shimon Gamliel did this. How does it say that
רב Rav would say is it a problem? No, it's not a
problem, the reason it's allowed is because he was only giving thanks.
How does it read? רב Rav would explain that the reason that
was allowed was, it's a funny way of saying it, then אודויי
הוא דקמודה. Aduye hu dekamode. אלא רשב"ג ורבי עקיבא, Ela Rashbag veRabbi
Akiva, they were just recognizing, giving thanks to God as opposed to
what? As well as well the the עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim you
say beautiful? I guess, דאמר מר, deamar mar, yeah, הרואה בריות טובות,
Haroe beriyot tovot, one who sees beautiful creatures, אומר, can say to
God, ברוך שככה ברא בעולמו, Baruch shekacha bara beolamo, you say blessed
are you God that you've created such a beautiful world. So the
question is, so how and in what case does רב say it's
אסור assur to say how beautiful it is? Is that it requires
that you that you actually direct your words to God, meaning if
I say to Michael, Michael, did you see how beautiful that building
is? Oh my God, you know whatever, that's not okay because I'm
not saying ברוך Baruch are you God that you've created such beauty.
Right, what did רבן שמעון גמליאל Rabban Shimon Gamliel say? He said
מה רבו מעשיך השם. Ma rabu maasecha Hashem. So maybe we're not
bothered with ר' עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. ר' עקיבא Rabbi Akiva just laughed.
He didn't actually say it was beautiful or anything. We're bothered with
רבן שמעון גמליאל. Rabban Shimon Gamliel. So what allows it is when
you focus it on God. It all comes from God. It's not,
oh the non-Jews are so brilliant, you know, the non-Jews, oh my
God, they have such beautiful music, they have such beautiful actresses or
whatever you say, that's making it about the non-Jews. If you make
it about God, God has created a beautiful world and you see
even the beauty even amongst the non-Jews or whatever, then all of
a sudden it undermines the non-Jewish world is not what's attractive. You
know, so that sort of seems to be to be the what
the point here. I don't think it's as narrow as Michael said
that it's only if you say it directly to the person. It
seems like the גמרא feels the problem is to say it about
them, not to them, but you have to do it in a
way that it's not about them, like that like there's a sense
of like I wish I was I wish I could be like
them, I wish I could be part of that world because it's
so unamazing that world and I can't be part of it. I
think that's the issue. But saying someone's beautiful is not saying I
want to be part of their world. A little bit, you know,
you watch the TV, you see all these you know you see
all yeah, oh my God, they're so they're so attractive and they're
so this whatever and there's a sense like it's better the grass
is always greener. You know and yeah people with young kids with
teenage kids I think can appreciate this, right? You even wrote a
letter to the editor once about that, didn't you? Something along those
lines? Anyway fine, okay, when the media has such an influence on
our minds if we let it you know. Right, and it's sort
of about oh my God like it's all seductive, it's all wanting
to be like that world, you know exactly. Okay, so now now
the גמרא gets to the issue of male lust. Okay, ולאיסתכולי מי
שרי? Velistakuli mi sharei? Forget about about saying words, how are you
allowed to be looking at these at this beautiful woman? Okay, מתיבי
ונשמרת מכל דבר רע, Metivei venishmarta mikol davar ra, this is
okay,
correct, we'll get to that. ונשמרת מכל דבר רע, Venishmarta mikol davar
ra, you should protect yourself against every evil thing, שלא יסתכל אדם
באשה נאה, Shelo yistakel adam beisha naah,
ואפילו
פנויה, veafilu pnuyah, don't look at a beautiful woman even if she's
unmarried, which is interesting. What, I'm not allowed to go on dating?
All right, so it's specifically in the context about trying to find
a wife that's a different story. But if it's סתם stam about
just trying to get sexual pleasure, you know through looking, through then
that's not allowed. באשת איש ואפילו
מכוערת, Beishet ish vaafilu mechueret, or a married woman even if she's
ugly, you know because that she's forbidden. So it's okay to look
at a single woman who's ugly in a sexual way? Anyway, but
all right, ולא
בבגדי צבע של אשה, Velo bevigdei tzeva shel isha, and not even
in and not even in the in the in the clothes... colored
garments because these would just lead to sexual thoughts. Even like on
the rack? Yeah, the גמרא's going to discuss that. ולא בחמור ולא
בחמורה ולא בחזיר ולא בחזירה ולא בעופות בזמן שנזקקין זה לזה Velo
bachamor velo bachamora velo bachazir velo bachazira velo be'ofot bizman shenizkakin ze
laze you can't even watch donkeys and whatever and animals when they're
copulating because it'll just lead to sexual thought. Okay, so now of
course the question here is I just need to pause for a
moment. What is the דבר רע? davar ra? Is the דבר רע
davar ra a sexual thought presumably? Another thing that we're going to
get to in a minute is also the possibility that it refers
to the fact that it will lead to זרע לבטלה, zera levatala,
to you know a wasting of seed and that that's the דבר
רע. davar ra. But it is a little bit disturbing that the
first word after דבר רע davar ra is לא יסתכל באשה, lo
yistakel be'isha, like to make the woman as like the evil object,
the seductress, women are evil, they create sexual thoughts in men, like
to blame all of the problems with men's sexual thought on the
women, right, blaming the victim, I mean you know whatever, it's all
that stuff that we know about. But anyway, but it doesn't seem
that that's the point of the גמרא. The דבר רע davar ra
is maybe the evil thought you know. The מהרש"א's Maharsha a little
bit bothered that why do we say דיבור dibur means a thought.
But anyway, but it does seem it's a thought because immediately we
go like even looking at animals copulating, you know, that's part of
the natural world, there's nothing evil about that, but what you're protecting
yourself is don't see things that will evoke these types of sexual
thoughts. Now of course I just have to say something that I
think this is like a major disservice that we do to all
of our young men and women, maybe more predominantly men, but both,
you know, is that whole focus on like not having sexual thoughts
because it's like it's not possible, like this is something that like
is just a natural part of being human, especially you know when
you're growing up and you know your hormones or whatever and your
body is developing sexually. And like we create such this obsession you
know for פרום frum young men who get you know who take
this stuff very seriously about such this obsession around sexual thoughts that
it just makes the problem worse. You know, it's like try not
to think about a pink elephant or whatever. You know, you're so
worried about your sexual thoughts. You know, if we just sort of
like let them happen and just acknowledge them and moved on, you
know, it would be the easiest thing, right, not the easiest thing,
but what I mean... So I think that this whole thing is
very religiously, you know, and emotionally, whatever, problematic, the emphasis on this.
And the גמרא says that one of the things אדם ניצול מהם
בכל יום adam nitzal mehem bechol yom is about הרהור עבירה, hirhur
aveira, sexual thoughts, you can't protect yourself from them. So if we
just allowed that and acknowledged that, you know, so I don't know
what to say, but I think that the high emphasis on this...
There's a lot of things in the גמרא, you know, לשון הרע
lashon hara is a lot worse, right? You know, it's really violating
a lot of prohibitions, you know. If only we obsessed as much
about לשון הרע lashon hara as we did about this. You know,
anyway, I think the obsession about this and then the way it
translates into you know like all the וידויים viduyim on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur and the תפילה זכה tefila zaka and all this type
of stuff,
it's counterproductive even to its own goals is what I'm saying, you
know? You're right also, I mean the girls think that you know,
I can't wear this or I have to wear this or that
and you know they feel... Yeah, that's a focus on צניעות, tzniut,
that's another problem, okay? But the problem is... and if I'm not
then I'll be the men... I understand, that's a different point and
which I will make another time when we get to that, but
this is the point I'm making right now. Anyway and if you
look at תוספות, okay, תוספות is going on another דרשה ונשמרת מן
drasha venishmarta min in a minute, which is going to be you
shouldn't have sexual thoughts in the day, it shouldn't lead to having
spilling semen at night. And you look at תוספות שלא יהרהר אדם
ביום, shelo yeharher adam bayom, he says האי קרא דרשה גמורה היא.
hai kra drasha gemura hi. It's a real דאורייתא De'oraita not to
have these types of thoughts. ולא אסמכתא כמו פרק נושא שנסתחפה, Velo
asmakhta kemo perek noseh shenispata, just make it... now that's debated, but
obviously that makes it obviously just one degree worse. Okay, and then
he says והקשה רב אלחנן vehiksha Rav Elchanan אם כן if it's
really a דאורייתא De'oraita מאי רבותיה דיחזקאל, mai revutei deYechezkel, why was
יחזקאל Yechezkel making praising
himself? דאמרינן פרק שני דחולין ונפשי לא נטמאה שלא הרהרתי ביום ובאתי
לידי טומאה בלילה. De'amrinan perek sheni deChulin venafshi lo nitame'ah shelo hirharti
bayom va'ati lidei tum'ah balaila. He was complimenting himself, oh, I'm at
such a high level I didn't have these sexual thoughts. Everybody's supposed
to do that if it's a real... if it's a real חובה!
hova! Right? והוא אמר Vehu amar ויש לומר Veish lomar מכל מקום
רבותא נימא מה שהיה מציל עצמו מהרהור mikol makom revuta nima ma
shehaya matzil etzmo mehirhur מה שאין כן בשאר אדם ma she'ein ken
bish'ar adam דאינו ניצול מהם בכל יום. de'eino nitzal mehem bechol yom.
Okay, but nobody else is able to achieve it. So what type
of הלכה halachic obligation is it that no normal person can do?
You know, on one hand he says it's דאורייתא De'oraita and on
the other hand he says but no one nowadays is able to
do it. There's לא תתאוה לא תחמוד lo tit'aveh lo tachmod yesterday...
Alright, that's different. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא says like that, so
anyway, so okay, going on, so don't have these sexual thoughts, don't
be מסתכל. mistakel. ואפילו מלא עיניים כמלאך המות. Ve'afilu malei einayim kemalach
hamavet. I never really got this line, but even if you're filled
with eyes like the angel of death. Apparently they had some image
of like the angel of death, like you know these monsters with
eyes all around, meaning you'll say how can I help but see?
Like you know it's just in front of me. I don't care
if you've got eyes in the back of your head, figure out
how not to look. Okay, now we're now going to digress a
little about the מלאך המות. malach hamavet. אמרו עליו על מלאך המות
Amru alav al malach hamavet they said about the מלאך המות malach
hamavet שכולו מלא עיניים shekulo malei einayim he's filled with eyes. ובשעת
פטירתו של חולה, Ubish'at petirato shel choleh, I don't know, it means
he sees everything that goes on in this earth, okay, when... when
a sick person is about to die, עומד מעל מראשותיו omed me'al
merashotav he stands above his head וחרבו שלופה בידו vecharbo shlufa beyado
his sword is drawn וטיפה של מרה תלויה בו vetipa shel mara
tluya bo and there's a drop of poison on the sword. כיון
שחולה רואה אותו Keivan shecholeh ro'eh oto
and you see him, he's... the sick person מזדעזע mizda'aze'a
he shudders. He trembles ופותח פיו ufoteach piv he opens his mouth
וזורקה לתוך פיו vezorka letoch piv and the poison goes into the
mouth. ממנה מתה mimena meta poison causes him to die. ממנה מסריח
mimena masriach it causes the body to rot after death. ממנה פניו
מוריקות mimena panav morikot and the face of and the face changes,
you know, after death. Anyway, the question is you're not allowed to
look at women. So what were they doing looking at women? So
the answer is קרן זוית הוי. keren zavit havai. It was around
the it was a corner. They bumped into them at the corner.
It wasn't like, okay, even if you're filled with eyes you should
close, close your eyes. Yeah, he was on הר הבית. Har HaBayit.
Maybe she turned a corner. I don't know what it was. He
wasn't intending to look, he wasn't intending to look, she suddenly walked
into his line of sight. Okay, but but now the problem is,
because I agree with Michael that I would much rather like to
interpret this הלכה halacha as הסתכלות, histaklut, an intentional gaze, particularly maybe
even a sexual gaze, right, a leer or whatever, but you know
a lustful gaze, but certainly an intentional gaze, like you're focusing to
look, you know, as opposed to saying like you happen to see,
doesn't mean oh my god you have to close your eyes. Okay,
but the the sense of this text as it limits the case
it was okay when they bumped into a corner which obviously wasn't
the case of הר הבית Har HaBayit anyway, you know, seems to
really sort of say you're supposed to go around with like blinders
on in front of your face. I don't know what to tell
you. Anyway, in some I heard that about a year ago some
חרדים charedim developed these glasses that actually blurred the it essentially blurred
the vision in front of you. I know. Enough that you could
walk across the street but not enough that God forbid you should
see any any woman. Okay, you know you have to have it
have like you know what do you call it have like you
know feature recognition so it only blurs when and okay, anyway. ולא
בבגדי צבע של אשה. velo bevigdei tzeva shel isha. Okay,
not in the colored garments of a woman. אמר רב יהודה. amar
Rav Yehuda. Now really? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel אפילו שטוחים על גבי כותל. afilu shtuchim agabei kotel.
Yeah, cause if a woman was wearing them then you'd be looking
at a woman. So he so he says it must mean that
even if they're just on the clothesline. So really though, how far
are we taking this? אמר רב פפא במכיר בעליהן. amar Rav Pappa
bamakir baaleihen. Okay, if you're going to say that it's only when
you recognize their owners. So when you see that oh beautiful yellow
dress, you're thinking about the that beautiful woman you saw wearing the
yellow dress and so on.
Okay. But he's talking about her wearing it though, which is interesting,
right? In other words she's allowed to have it go out in
the street with
it... Yeah, correct. Correct. אבא, Abba, correct. אמר רבא amar Rava דייקא
נמי, dika nami, no, that's an important point because, you know, we
have translated all of these concerns about about men's sexual thoughts and
put it on women and about how women have to cover their
bodies in not just in a tactful way and Michael is absolutely
correct, the גמרא is very clear that the responsibility is the man's
and not the woman's and yes, the same way we do an
injury to our young men by focusing them on their whole sexual
thoughts, all the messages we give around women covering up their bodies
I mean people should dress modestly, people should act modestly, but the
fact that we make women responsible for men's sexual thoughts is also
extremely counterproductive and unhealthy. And you're absolutely correct, women can wear these
colored dresses. That's not the problem, the problem is what men are
doing. Okay. אמר רבא דייקא נמי
דקתני ולא בבגדי צבע של
אשה. amar Rava dika nami dektani velo bevigdei tzeva shel isha. It
says colored women's colored garments. ולא קתני ולא
בבגדים צבעוניים, velo ktani velo bevigadim tzevoniyim, just say colored garments. Colored
garments obviously refers to women. It's like saying don't watch don't look
at women's dresses. Why don't you just say don't look at dresses?
So adding the word women's emphasizes that you know the woman and
therefore evokes that image of that woman in your mind. שמע מינה.
אמר רב חסדא הני מילי בעתיקין. amar Rav Chisda hani mili beatikin.
Now even that is only a problem if they're if they're old,
meaning if the woman's been wearing them, so there's this identification. אבל
בחדתי לית בן בה. aval bechadatti leit ban bah. If the woman
just happens to buy them in the store and hasn't worn it
yet, just cause you happen to know that this woman bought this
dress isn't I mean I wonder what are you doing knowing that
this woman anyway whatever anyway it's not a problem. It's only once
she's been wearing it. דאי לא תימא הכי, de’i lo teima hachi,
if you don't say that, אנן מנא לשפוריא היכי יהבינן? anan mana
lashpuria heichi yahavinan? How do we give our clothes to the tailor
in order to make adjustments, right? How can the tailor be making
adjustments? There he is, he knows that this woman gave him the
the dress, he's making adjustments, he so he's looking at the clothes
at the clothes and he's thinking of the woman. Of course the
question be how can we give them to adjust after we've been
wearing it for a year, you know maybe need to take it
in, take it out, whatever. Anyway but we're not asking that question.
Anyway so it must be dry cleaners. Right. Dry cleaners. It must
be if it's new it's not an issue. So the גמרא says
maybe you're right that if it's new it's not an issue but
that's not a proof. There's another explanation for that. The גמרא says
ולטעמך velateimei and according
to your reasoning,
חד אמר רב יהודה chad amar Rav Yehuda מין במינו מותר להכניס
כמכחול בשפופרת min bemino mutar lehachnis kemichol bashoferet or a farmer whatever
a husbandry I think or whatever anyway is dealing with animals and
having them you know making them copulate and he's actually taking the
taking you know the male organ and you know taking the penis
and inserting it into the vagina of the of the cow whatever
he's doing. כמכחול בשפופרת kemichol bashoferet is like a eyelash like a
what's called an eyelash what's it called applicator into the
tube. Okay. I hope I hope the picture is of the eyelash
tube. Anyway. So the גמרא says הכא מיסתכל, hacha mistakel, he's looking
and we're said you're not supposed to look at animals copulating. So
the גמרא says...
The point is if you're doing it as professionally, you're focused on
the profession, okay, and הכא נמי בעבידתיה טריד, hacha nami b'avideiteih tarid,
here too the same thing, and we're not so and we're not
really concerned, so don't prove me anything about the fact that we
have a dry cleaner or a tailor working on dresses, that doesn't
prove about other contexts. Of course it raises interesting questions that come
up in שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch about men should they be taking
certain professions like, you know, can you be a photographer of women's
bags? Exactly, and not everything is בעבידתיה טריד, avideiteih tarid, exactly to
the same degree, exactly that. You know, can a guy go ahead
and be a hairdresser for women and oh it's בעבידתיה טריד, avideiteih
tarid, right, you know, sometimes the בעבידתיה avideiteih is sexually charged or
could be or whatever. So anyway, separate conversation. Anyway, אמר מר, amar
mar, let's get back to the מלאך המות. Malach HaMavet. That's what
I really want to talk about. ממנה מת, mimena met, so נימא,
neima, so if he dies by this poison, נימא פליגי דאבוה דשמואל,
neima pligi d'Avud Shmuel, this argues on the father of Shmuel. דאמר
אבוה דשמואל, De'amar Avud Shmuel, אמר לי מלאך המות, amar li Malach
HaMavet, the angel of death said to me, אילו דחשינא ליקרא דברייתא,
ilu d'chashina likra dibriyata, if I were not concerned with כבוד הבריות,
kvod habriyot, with the honor of human beings, הוי פרענא בית השחיטה
כבהמה, havai parata beit hashchita k'beheima, I would slaughter them and like
like, you know, their neck would be slit like an animal's neck.
So, you know, with like so that's how I would kill them.
But instead I have more compassion. But the point and basically I
only do the cutting inside the body, not outside the body. But
it sounds like it's through an act of cutting. It sounds like
maybe he cuts I don't know, you know, the trachea and the
esophagus just not from the outside. And you're saying it's poison. So
the גמרא says דילמא ההוא טיבא מחתכו ליה לסימנים, dilma hahu tiba
mechatchu lei le'simanim, oh maybe that no, it could be both. The
poison causes like burns through, it's an acid, you know, burns through
the trachea and the esophagus, so it's both a type of a
cutting and a poison. Michael I really don't care. ממנה מסריח, mimena
maschriach, so it causes the body to rot. מסייע ליה לרבי חנינא
בר כהנא, misayei lei le'Rabbi Chanina bar Kahana, דאמר בי רב, d'amar
bei Rav, הרוצה שלא
יסריח מתו יהפכנו על פניו. harotzeh shelo yasriach meto yapchenu al panav.
If you don't want the body to rot, turn it on its
side, so that maybe I don't know the poison doesn't go in
the mouth, he dies another way because he doesn't see the מלאך
המות Malach HaMavet over him. It sounds like the body's already dead,
so I don't know, maybe it causes some of the poison to
go out of the body, I don't know. תנו רבנן, tano rabbanan,
we want to just read this one last thing about sexual thoughts,
famous גמרא. ונשמרת מכל
דבר רע, v'nishmarta mikol davar ra, protect yourself against every evil thing,
we said that's about sexual thought. And here the גמרא clarifies what's
the problem with sexual thoughts, because you could say the problem with
sexual thoughts has nothing to do with seminal emission. It has to
do with the fact that it's taking your mind away from, you
know, higher higher, you know, higher purposes. You're not thinking about God
if you're thinking too much about sex. Okay, but the גמרא here
says it's about seminal emission. This גמרא. שלא יהרהר אדם ביום ויבא
לידי טומאה בלילה. shelo yeharher adam beyom v'yavo lidei tuma balayla. Don't
start thinking have sexual thoughts in the day, it'll lead you to
have seminal emission at night. And because the end of the verse
is because after it says ונשמרת מכל דבר רע v'nishmarta mikol davar
ra as רש״י Rashi says, the verse goes on to speak about
כי יהיה לך דבר מקרה לילה, ki yihiyeh lecha davar mikreh layla,
right, if you have that after that it speaks about seminal emission
in the verse itself. So here we're reading it that מכל דבר
רע mikol davar ra is not just protect, you know, the way
you protect yourself against seminal emission is now of course that verse
was about a need to leave the camp, it wasn't it was
specifically in the context of of the camp at a time of
war and so on, but the גמרא is more generalizing it and
talking about not having sexual thoughts in general during the day. In
the בית מדרש Beit Midrash though? I understand. Okay. מכאן אמר רבי
פנחס בן יאיר, mikan amar Rabbi Phineas ben Yair, famous statement of
Rabbi, yes? It's interesting the way they're interweaving the angel of death.
Oh yes, I meant to say that. Yeah, it keeps on going
back and forth. I think the point is similar to the גמרא
about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and about that this beauty is all
going to waste away, is it sort of trying to sort of
maybe either like, you know, help us appreciate the transitory nature that
we're all so we shouldn't be too seduced by the beauty and
take an after it maybe a way of helping us deal with,
you know, but I have these sexual thoughts, I do find this
or whatever and like, you know, try try to get a recognition
that everybody's going to die, you're going to die or whatever I
don't know, you know, I don't know, that's the way I read
it, but yes, it was very interesting the way it kept on
interweaving it I think it's to try to either a scare tactic
or I'd rather say it a little bit better, oh you better
not be good because angel death going to come kill you, or
maybe just more just to recognize the transitory nature of our present.
Okay. Okay. מכאן אמר רבי פנחס בן יאיר, mikan amar Rabbi Phineas
ben Yair, famous statement, תורה מביאה לידי זהירות, Torah mevia lidei zehirut,
Torah brings to to being נזהר, nishar, נזהר nishar means like careful
against sinning, this basic framework about ten steps to lead to רוח
הקודש Ruach HaKodesh and תחיית המתים Techiyat HaMetim is the framework that
the מסילת ישרים Mesillat Yesharim uses for his work. He speaks about
what you have to do to get each step, okay, some of
these steps are not so clear what they are, if you want
more elaboration you can see the מסילת ישרים's Mesillat Yesharim take on
it. Okay, so anyway, תורה מביאה לידי זהירות. Torah mevia lidei zehirut.
If you learn Torah it leads you to be careful not to
sin. זהירות מביאה לידי זריזות. zehirut mevia lidei zerizut. Care of sin
leads you to have alacrity, you know, being, you know, eager to
go ahead and do מצוות. mitzvot. זריזות מביאה לידי נקיות. zerizut mevia
lidei nekiut. That alacrity leads to cleanliness. What type of that is
physical cleanliness? So רש״י Rashi says that it means I mean just,
you know, it means like clean from sin, it's a higher level
of of not just not sinning but being clean from sin. The
מהרש״א Maharsha has a very interesting read about this that these are
stages in your day. Okay, so you're just careful in general from
sinning, you wake up in the morning and you're and you have
זריזות. zerizut. Just, you know, getting out of bed to serve God.
Go to bed earlier? Yeah. If you get out of the bed
early, then you're able to take a shower and you're able to
bathe and to be clean. He says that. Yeah. So you're not
rushing to דאוון daven without taking a without without bathing, it's important,
cleanliness is close to godliness. נקיות מביאה לידי פרישות Nikiah miviah lidei
prishus that leads to separating, so separating is like not only not
sinning, but actually more like asceticism, like, you know, like not even
engaging in things that are permissible as a to bring on a
higher level. The מהרש״א Maharsha reads it as after you're clean and
you take your shower, you דאוון. daven. And when you דאוון daven
your hands are פרושות לשמים prushos lashamayim are spread out to heaven,
or you're separating yourself from the physical world, you're focusing on God
for that moment. פרישות מביאה לידי טהרה Prishus miviah lidei tahara that
brings to a higher level than being clean is being pure, right?
So you know, it's even a higher stage. Okay, the מהרש״א Maharsha
says that means after דאווענינג davening you do תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah.
טהרה מביאה לידי Tahara miviah lidei now here's a question about the
גירסא, girsa, we'll read the side גירסא, girsa, קדושה. kidusha. Oh no,
actually he says that the טהרה tahara means I think like how
like you eat in a way that's pure. Anyway, then it brings
to holiness, right now you because you know you're pure, why do
you go pure? So you can go into the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, to become holy. So once you're pure, you're able to enter
into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and be holy like a you're
able to enter into קדושה. kidusha. The מהרש״א Maharsha says that means
you do תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah after you דאוון daven and eat.
קדושה מביאה לידי ענווה Kidusha miviah lidei anava that leads to humility.
Okay, that's interesting that after you're holy, maybe that's exactly the problem,
you're holy you think you're great, anyway, hopefully you can both be
holy and be humble. The מהרש״א Maharsha says it means after תלמוד
תורה Talmud Torah you go to your workday, and in your workday,
you know, the fact that you started your day with דאווענינג davening
and תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah allows you to have a humility. Okay,
ענווה מביאה לידי יראת חטא anava miviah lidei yiras cheit
that brings to fear of sin. It's so funny, you would think
יראת חטא yiras cheit came way earlier if you're being נזהר nizhar
and נקי noki and טהור tahor and קדוש, kadosh, right? Like you
know, so obviously this יראת חטא yiras cheit must be a very
high level of יראת חטא. yiras cheit. יראת חטא מביאה לידי חסידות
Yiras cheit miviah lidei chasidus
which is you know a it's interesting, like the highest level here,
you think it's all that separating from the world, but חסידות chasidus
is kindness, is all about like giving, you know, acts of kindness
or whatever, but maybe חסיד chasid doesn't mean חסד chesed here, maybe
חסידות chasidus even means a greater sense of separation from this world.
חסידות מביאה לידי רוח הקודש Chasidus miviah lidei ruach hakodesh that brings
to divine spirit. רוח הקודש מביאה לידי תחיית המתים Ruach hakodesh miviah
lidei techiyas hameisim and that brings to the resurrection of the dead.
The מהרש״א Maharsha that means that that רוח הקודש ruach hakodesh is
when you go to bed at night, your thoughts are pure and
that don't have thoughts in the day that leads to s- whatever
seminal emission at night, and the תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim is when
you wake up the next morning, your body gets re- re-ensouled. Anyway,
cute read of the מהרש״א. Maharsha. Anyway, but try to lead a
life of total purity and that you'll be free, you know, and
that and that leads to this טהרה tahara as opposed to טומאה,
tumah, which if you have sexual thoughts it'll lead to sexual im-
to whatever seminal emission. Okay, וחסידות גדולה מכולם vechasidus gedolah mikulam and
חסידות chasidus is the higher highest level, because it comes right before
רוח הקודש. ruach hakodesh. שנאמר, shene'emar, if we had if we switch
the גירסא, girsa, אז דברת בחזון לחסידיך, az dibarta vechazon lachasidecha, then
you spoke in a vision to your חסידים. chasidim. ופליגי דרבי יהושע
בן לוי דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, upligi de-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, ענווה גדולה מכולם, anava gedolah mikulam, ענווה
anava is the highest level. שנאמר רוח ה׳ אלקים עלי יען משח
ה׳ אותי לבשר ענווים. shene'emar ruach Hashem Elokim alai ya'an mashach Hashem
osi levasser anavim. The spirit of God was on me, so the
thing that comes before רוח הקודש ruach hakodesh is because God has
anointed me with the flesh of the of the humble. חסידים לא
נאמר אלא ענווים הא למדת שענווה גדולה מכולם. chasideem lo ne'emar ella
anavim ha lamadta she-anava gedolah mikulam. What is the highest level right
before רוח הקודש? ruach hakodesh? Okay, it was right? From ה׳ Hashem
and then leads to ענווה? anava? What? Doesn't the same רוח ה׳
ruach Hashem is leading you to ענווה? anava?
No, יען, ya'an, because ענווה anava preceded it, that's why. Okay, we're
going to have to end here, we will pick up with